All right. Well, let's go ahead and talk
about Georgia O'Keeffe. So,
um if I think if people were to do like
a word association with Georgia
O'Keeffe, they would um think of New
Mexico. She's just really closely
associated with the state. She spent a
lot of time there. Before we get into
her art, just kind of a real quick bio
of Georgia O'Keeffe. So, she's really uh
American what's known as modernism uh
pioneer, meaning modern art. She was
part of what's known as the avant-garde,
meaning uh people that were uh driving
change, so to speak, in the art and
cultural world. Uh she trained entirely
in the United States, which not maybe a
big deal now, but in Georgia O'Keeffe's
era, most artists at some point in time
would go to Europe to study uh like the
old masters and things like that. She
didn't do that, so American train is
pretty interesting. Uh really wide
variety of subjects. She's most known
for her flowers and New Mexico
landscapes, but she also did a lot of
abstraction. She did these really cool
New York Cityscapes uh and various other
things. And then, what's Georgia
O'Keeffe's style? What's really
distinctive? You can kind of know it
when you see it, but the um kind of key
components that
really bold colors, a lot of variety of
colors. We've been doing these programs
trying to figure out what Georgia
O'Keeffe's favorite color is, and I
don't know if we've ever come to a
uh
consensus on that. And then, she uses
what's called magnified shapes. We'll
see that a little bit later. Simplified
details, and then a lot of
juxtaposition.
Uh she was married to photographer and
modern art promoter Alfred Stieglitz,
and she's one of the world's great
artists, not just a great woman artist,
not just a great American artist, a
great artist, period. Um so, let's go
ahead
and talk Well, first, we'll do a trivia
question.
How many paintings did Georgia O'Keeffe
create? What do you think? Was it 50?
Was it 173?
Was it 17,294?
It was about 2,000 paintings. So, she
really cranked them out, really prolific
artist. Uh I have to admit, I've not
seen all 2,000,
but I've seen most of them, at least all
the um well-known ones and the ones in
public museums. But yeah, 2,000
paintings, I mean, that's pretty
incredible, uh especially when you
consider some paintings you might be
able to do in an hour or two, but some
might take several days or weeks. So,
pretty interesting in that regard. And
then, when we do these uh programs on
American art, I always like to people to
kind of consider the what's known as the
American experience.
Um so, how does art and artists kind of
visually uh document and record what's
going on around them? Uh it's kind of
like part of the historical record, so
to speak. And then, how do artists kind
of inspire and influence uh American pop
culture? Georgia O'Keeffe has had a
really huge influence on America in that
regard. So, something kind of keep in
the back of your mind as we go through
the art tonight. Uh let's see. So, let's
talk about the New Mexico years. So,
uh Georgia O'Keeffe,
probably the place um
head and shoulders above any other
geographic location that she's
associated with, but she actually spent
time in a lot of different states. Uh
so, Georgia O'Keeffe was actually born
in Wisconsin.
Uh she spent a couple years living in
Chicago.
Uh she was in New York
uh city. Uh she also lived in Virginia
for a while. She lived in Texas, where
Joanne and I are at. And then, of
course, New Mexico. So, um you know, if
you were thinking maybe she was born and
raised and lived in New Mexico her whole
life, that uh would not be true. She
actually lived in quite a few different
places, but New Mexico is the place that
she's most closely associated with. And
I love [snorts] New Mexico. It's uh our
neighbors to the west. Uh if you've
never been there before, it's one of the
most beautiful states in America. It's
known as the land of enchantment. Uh it
has the capital of Santa Fe. The largest
city is Albuquerque. And interestingly
enough,
New Mexico only became a state in 1912,
and Georgia O'Keeffe visited New Mexico
for the first time in 1929, so just 17
years later. And then, also too, um
even today, New Mexico is somewhat of a
open space. Um there's 2.3 million
people live there, which that's about
the size of the
uh say San Antonio or Austin, Texas
metro areas. Uh so, imagine that number
of people spread out across the whole
state. But when Georgia O'Keeffe first
visited there, there were only 420,000
people in New Mexico, uh the whole
entire state. So, that's pretty amazing.
And I don't know of any
geographical places that are as closely
associated with Georgia O'Keeffe or with
an artist as New Mexico is associated
with Georgia O'Keeffe. I mean, like say
like, "Well, you have um see Andy Warhol
in New York City, and I don't know,
maybe Monet in Giverny or something like
that." But uh you know, not a lot of
artists are so closely identified with
like a single
uh geographic space. So,
we'll go look at some art in just a
minute, but before we do that, um
Joanne, Brad, Patty, any thoughts on
Georgia O'Keeffe, New Mexico before we
start looking at some cool art?
Well, one one thing that is amazing
about her, and you noted that she's not
just a great woman or American artist,
she's a great artist. She had so many
distinct periods, and yet they are all
pretty wonderful, which is also an
interesting achievement. I mean, she did
very different things at very different
times and places in her life. And um
there's something unique about every
single one of those periods.
Oh, that's a great point, Patty. And
yeah, people should really be on the
lookout for that, because her art really
does kind of change and evolve over
time. So, I I feel like a lot of people
might be typecasters, "Oh, she just made
these flowers and New Mexico
landscapes." But that's not the case at
all.
What about you, Brad and Joanne? Any
thoughts on Georgia O'Keeffe before we
start looking at her? Oh, go ahead,
Patty.
Was Was someone going to say something?
Go ahead.
The floor is yours.
Oh, okay.
Georgia um
I'm getting this echo on my end. It's
really annoying.
Well, I can't hear I can't hear the echo
from you, Joanne, so I think you're
fine. Oh, okay.
Okay, great. That's good to know.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay. Um when you're a must-see
in Santa Fe is the Georgia O'Keeffe
Museum.
Uh yeah, that's just a fabulous place.
Yeah.
And yeah, Georgia O'Keeffe said in an
interview that she painted flowers
because they're cheap.
>> [clears throat]
>> Uh she said, "You know, that that
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, she's No, she said it's
it's because of any symbolic thing or uh
subconscious Freudian type of thing. But
she said, "You know, when you paint
flowers, you don't have to hire a model
and you know, make sure they're standing
in a certain way.
And of course, when you're with
landscapes, you have to watch the
weather.
Mhm. But you know, flowers are just a
lot easier to work with.
Oh yeah, make things easier.
And of course, they're beautiful.
And because she was experimenting with
color, so yeah. Well,
on Patty's point earlier, I would say
that there was no period
of learning that I saw in any of the art
that we studied of hers, you know. It
was
For her, every one was a learning
experience, but um you know, we don't
have a period of years where all it was
all
something sort of mundane, and she was
putting out beauty right from the start.
She's Well, that's a good point, too. I
never thought about that, Brad. But
yeah, you're right. There's not like
there didn't really seem like there was
much of a learning curve with her. But
my art my artwork would be stick
figures, you know, so
All right. Well, let's um continue on.
So, just like really brief biographical
information. So, like So, how did
Georgia O'Keeffe, this woman who lived
in all these different places, how did
she even end up in New Mexico? And it's
kind of an unusual uh story. So, her
husband, Alfred Stieglitz,
uh when Georgia O'Keeffe first met him,
he was married to somebody else.
And so, he and Georgia started uh a
relationship. Uh Alfred ends up
divorcing his wife, and then he ends up
marrying Georgia O'Keeffe. Interestingly
enough, when they were alive for much of
their marriage, uh Alfred Stieglitz was
the more well-known
uh art figure. Not for their whole time
that they were together, but
particularly for the early years. He was
a very um influential photographer, and
also a modern art promoter. He had a art
gallery in New York City, promoted a lot
of modern artists. So, a really like
important um historical figure in the
art world. But today, he's kind of
mostly known for being Georgia
O'Keeffe's husband, which, you know,
nothing wrong with that. Uh and he and
Georgia uh began a relationship in 1918,
and they were married in 1924.
And you know, back then, they didn't
really get into the whole uh wedding
photo thing like they do now. This is
the only photo I've ever seen of their
wedding day. Um if someone else has seen
any different ones, you can let me know.
And they got married at a friend's house
in Cliffside, New Jersey. Oh, how about
that? On December 11th, 1924.
If you know where that is.
Um
but unfortunately,
five years after they were married,
Stieglitz had an affair with some other
woman. Uh and Georgia O'Keeffe was
really distraught by this, as you can
imagine.
Um and so, she's trying to figure out
what she's going to do. Is she going to
stay with Stieglitz? Is she going to
dump him? And one of Georgia's friends
said, "You know what? You should get
away from New York City and come out to
New Mexico with me. Take a vacation.
It'll be good for you." So, that's what
she ends up doing.
Um and while she's out in New Mexico, uh
her and Stieglitz are exchanging letters
back and forth and talking on the phone.
He's trying to get her back. Uh and
eventually, after several months, she
does end up coming back to New York
City, and they do continue on with their
marriage. Um I always think this is a
hilarious photo if you know the context
of it. So, when I first saw this photo,
I think, "Oh, that's a really nice photo
of her. I liked it a lot." But, the
context of this photo is Stieglitz, who
was a photographer, he took this photo
of Georgia O'Keeffe after she came back
to New York after they had been
separated for several months. And I
don't know, maybe I'm reading too much
into it, but she kind of has this
interesting look on her face.
I agree. Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> Oh, you I don't think you're reading too
much into it.
Yeah, yeah. He he's got that infamous
look, the look.
>> [laughter]
>> Right. Um, so yeah, this kind of an
interesting uh photo. So, the whole uh
New Mexico thing
it was a big moment for her both
personally and professionally.
Personally, just because, like I said,
her husband had cheated on her. They
were she was thinking about dumping him.
Uh, she goes out to New Mexico, but she
really discovers this whole uh New
Mexico scene, so to speak, uh and it
really influences her art for the rest
of her life. So, kind of unusual um
uh change in trajectory both personally
and professionally uh for Georgia
O'Keeffe. So, let's start looking at
some of the art that she made. So, this
was actually a painting that she did on
her first trip out there. So, while she
was out there trying to um
uh
figure out what she was going to do and
uh all that kind of personal stuff,
she starts making art while she's out
there. And so, this is a painting from
1929. Now, remember, uh at this point in
time, New Mexico had only been a state
for a few years uh when Georgia O'Keeffe
went out there. And of course, 1920 is
the year the Depression started. Um, but
this is really kind of like a classic
Georgia O'Keeffe painting from this era
because remember, when you have these
magnified shapes, which what that means
is pretend you're looking at something
through a magnifying glass. So, the uh
image is much more up close and
personal. And then, the forms are very
simplified. She leaves out a lot of
details. And those are kind of like two
characteristics you see in Georgia
O'Keeffe's artwork over and over again.
I feel like a lot of people when they
see Georgia O'Keeffe's artwork, they can
immediately identify it, which in and of
itself is pretty incredible because to
stand out as an artist when there's been
so many artists throughout the course of
time is quite extraordinary. Um,
but if you're trying to like, what makes
an O'Keeffe an O'Keeffe, um two of the
things are the magnified shapes and the
simplified forms that you see here.
That even sounds good together,
magnified shapes and simplified forms.
Oh, thank you. I appreciate that. Maybe
it'd be a name of a rock band or
something or for a movie.
It's just one of those great phrases.
Well, thank you. I wish I could take
credit for it, but
uh
I'm sure somebody else came up with it.
Um, we've talked before about, what do
you think Georgia O'Keeffe's favorite
color is?
Uh, I don't think we ever got a
definitive answer because she seems like
she uses the whole uh whole rainbow, so
to speak, but she does use black.
Fair enough. Maybe not as much as uh
uh Edouard Manet, but quite a bit. And I
love this painting. It's one of my
favorites. It's called the Lawrence
Tree.
>> And she also made this one on her first
trip to New Mexico. So, in 1929, uh the
reason why it's called the Lawrence
Tree, D.H. Lawrence was an English
writer. You may have heard of uh some of
his works. He's most known for Lady
Chatterley's Lover. And he was living in
a ranch in Taos, New Mexico, which is
where Georgia O'Keeffe was staying at on
her first uh trip. And this painting is
a really unique perspective. It's
laying on the ground looking upwards
towards the sky with this big giant
ponderosa pine
um over the top. I don't know, kind of
someone said it
uh when we did the program before, I
don't know if you remember, uh they said
it looked like an octopus. I was like,
"Oh, yeah, I can see that." Catherine
sees a squid. Oh, a squid. Yeah, that
too.
What a great phrase. Kim says, "I love
the tree roots grounding us in the
heavens."
You know, that's a good uh way to think
about it as well. So, appreciate that.
And again, great colors, a lot of great
shapes. Notice the simplified forms
again. That's kind of a characteristic
of much of
uh Georgia O'Keeffe's artwork.
Yeah, I like the blue
blue background.
Uh, it's almost like almost like the sky
with the stars.
Yeah, and it's just a really I mean I
mean, think about it. We do these
programs all the time. How many program
how many artworks can you think of of a
tree from, you know, this perspective?
It's usually a tree like we're facing
the tree. Um, it's not this uh unusual
perspective. So, that in and of itself
was a great clever idea.
And then, here is D.H. Lawrence. And
this is the ranch. So, this is a pretty
popular tourist attraction now. Um,
people come from all over to see it.
When Georgia O'Keeffe was visiting, it
wasn't I mean, it was a place that
people knew about, but it wasn't like
the, you know, top uh you know, it
wasn't like going to Disneyland.
But, she sought it out uh cuz she knew
of him. She had heard about this tree uh
and she wanted to go check it out
herself in person. And you can go see it
yourself when you visit New Mexico.
And so again, kind of the um
a a view of like what the tree would
have been like. Um, so here you go. So
again, imagine And Lawrence, the reason
why this tree was important for him, he
used to sit under this tree or even lay
under it and look up at the sky and he
would use it as inspiration for his
writing. Um, and so that was one reason
why Georgia O'Keeffe wanted to go see it
and perhaps get inspired, which
apparently it had the same effect on her
because she made this really cool
painting.
If I were trying to make this painting,
I would get so bogged down in all those
little tiny branches.
And it just
>> [clears throat]
>> it just speaks about
her style is that she could boil things
down and make them both more impressive
and less complicated than they were at
the same time.
Well, that yeah, I appreciate you
mentioned that, Patty, cuz yeah, I mean,
I would have the same exact problem.
You'd be like, "Gee, how am I going to
do this?" Um, but yeah, notice she kind
of simplifies things. And you know, we
still get the same effect, but um just
what more like efficient, so to speak.
You get the essence though. You get the
majesty of this tree
almost in in greater perspective than
the actual tree. If you
I'm not trying to down the real tree.
It's it's it's not that. It's just that
I I'm fascinated by how she could see
this complicated thing and go, "Oh,
yeah, I see the basics right there."
Mhm. Oh, yeah. It's just extraordinary.
Peralin has a great point. She said in
the chat, "It is the sky with stars."
Exclamation point. So, yeah, I agree.
Um, let's see. If you go visit in person
the museum, here's the gallery label.
Uh, "O'Keeffe found endless beauty and
inspiration in nature.
On her first trip to Taos, New Mexico,
O'Keeffe visited the ranch of writer
D.H. Lawrence. This dream-like, which I
think that's another great way to
describe it, composition was inspired by
a tree on the property. Lawrence was
known to lie at the base of the trunk to
look at the branches silhouetted against
the night sky. She visited Lawrence's
ranch to experience the same unusual
perspective beneath this fabled
ponderosa pine. Here, O'Keeffe presents
us with a view of the trunk and branches
silhouetted against the night sky." So,
there you have it.
Very nice indeed. One of my hard to say
which painting of Georgia O'Keeffe's is
my favorite, but I'd put this one on the
list. I really like this one a lot.
Well, in the way Yeah, and it is that
effect of grounding in the heavens,
which is again, turns
one sense of reality upside down, so
that would be dream-like, wouldn't it?
Oh, yeah. And I guess just maybe some
words to think about like this painting.
Like, oh yeah, it is dream-like. It is
has this really unique perspective.
Again, I can't I can't think of any
other paintings we've seen. Maybe we
have, I just don't remember, that were
from the ground uh looking up at a tree.
Uh, it's got the beautiful night sky
with the blue. And then of course, the
silhouette uh of the tree against the
background. Just I don't know, really
amazing.
Even the way it's based in the upper uh
left-hand corner,
who would think of
placing a tree in that,
you know, position on the canvas.
Well, yeah, that's a good point, too.
Like, how come it's not in the bottom
middle? I'm not suggesting it should be,
but that's what most people uh would do.
So, yeah, the the position of it makes
it even more interesting as well.
Yeah, I think that position suggests
eternity.
Ah. Well, there you go. Grounded in the
heavens, yeah.
Yeah, I never thought about that, but
that's a good point.
Um, let's see. And then, here's a
close-up of the squid. I mean, the
octopus. I mean, the tree.
It's almost kind of abs-
partially abstract just because the way
it's um
put together.
And what is
In one context, an abstract is taking
the details from something, the key
points.
And that's exactly what she's done.
That's her perspective of the tree.
Oh, yeah. Mhm. The essentials.
Yeah, the essentials, right. That's a
good way to put the essentials.
Um, let's see. She was also fascinated
by these pueblos that they have in Taos.
And if you like, I can't stress enough,
if you ever get a chance to be go to New
Mexico, you've never been there. It's
just really an incredible place.
Um,
and she was really inspired by these and
she ends up making a lot of paintings of
the pueblos. So, here's one of the more
well-known one. This is at a really nice
museum in Indianapolis, the Eiteljorg
Museum, which has a lot of um things
related to Native Americans and American
Indians. And they're not quite sure
exactly when she painted this, but they
do know it was kind of early in her um
stay in New Mexico. But, this pueblo is
pretty old. It was built uh between the
year 1000 AD and 1450. Uh, and again,
going back to this uh Georgia O'Keeffe
and the whole simplified forms things,
you can really see that kind of like
Patty was saying a minute ago where
she's just kind of focusing on the
essentials and kind of skipping out the
rest of the stuff.
And then there's a lot of cool churches
in New Mexico, especially in Taos. And
here is one that is a popular tourist
attraction that Georgia O'Keeffe was
also inspired by. So she ended up making
some paintings. Now, of course, these
aren't the paintings she made. On the
left is a vintage postcard and the right
is a more modern photo, but this is a
very
distinctive church.
And it looks like this because it was
made from adobe, which is this very
heavy like bricks that are made out of
mud among other things.
And Georgia O'Keeffe ended up doing a
number of paintings of this structure
over the course of her career,
particularly early on in her years in
New Mexico.
Yeah,
you're used to seeing like cathedrals
and stuff and they're very linear and
intricate. And again, you've got the
essentials,
but these are so curvilinear.
Yeah, and again, the simplified forms
and notice the different perspective.
So, you know, these are three paintings
of the same structure, but they're very,
very different because of the things
that she chose to focus on.
So, in the one in the bottom left, she's
focused on the front. The one in the
top, she's focused on the back. And then
the one on the right, she's focused on
one of the
two of the crosses in the window.
It's an interesting perspective there.
It almost
it almost evoke a rear view of the
Sphinx.
Oh, yeah, yeah, you know, I didn't think
about that, but yeah, a good point.
Let's see. So, this is a 1930. So,
again, she goes out there 1929 and she'd
pretty much be
returning yearly for many, many years
until she moved out there permanently.
And this is called Front of Ranchos
Church. Ranchos Church. The church was
built in 1772,
pretty amazing that four years before
the Declaration of Independence.
And so that kind of
contextual connection historically. And
then this is the front view. So, you got
the wall and the gate.
Now, there's a reason why these don't
look anything like the revolutionary the
centers of the revolution because this
was Spanish at the time.
Yeah, right. Yeah, New this is New
Mexico, not not New England. Yeah.
Let's go go ahead, Joan.
Yes, I just love I just love the beige
against the blue sky
and the clouds, you know, wonderfully
done.
>> very clean.
Oh, yeah.
And those little spritzes of green.
Yeah, I mean, she had such a great I
mean, you know, it's part of the thing
of being an artist, you have to come up
with ideas, you know, it's like being a
musician, you have to come up with songs
or director, you got to come up with
movie ideas. And she was really great at
coming up with these unique ideas
from these different perspectives. And
again, same thing, 1929, this is a
close-up view of the gate, which is not
something people I think would normally
focus on.
And here's what Georgia O'Keeffe had to
say about this building. It is one of
the most beautiful buildings in the
United States by the early Spaniards. I
had to paint it, the back several times,
the
>> [snorts]
>> Oops, your voice just dropped.
My statement that whole or better than
the whole good.
So, if you're wondering why she only
painted a portion of the building, there
you have it. Words from Georgia O'Keeffe
herself.
And again, so these simplified forms,
we've talked about that, just kind of
leaving out details like Patty said,
just focusing on the essentials, so to
speak. And then also interesting in this
one. So, you know, this is a man-made
structure,
but it's of course made out of natural
materials and it's in a natural setting
on the ground. But, you know, where does
the kind of the man-made start
the natural world start or vice versa?
And which where do they end at? They
kind of
mix together in that regard.
Yeah, even the clouds in this and you
wouldn't think you would notice the
clouds with all the intricacy of the
building, but it's like the clouds pop
it.
Yeah, and then it and it adds a nice
like visual, you know, makes it more
interesting than if it was just like a
plain structure.
>> And then if you're not familiar with
this, go go ahead, someone someone was
going to say something. Yeah.
And I'm seeing if it
for the picture with the left, also the
more peachy beige
against the very, very light beige.
I mean, again, that pops it, too.
Oh, yeah, nice contrast. Yeah. Let's
see. So, here's an actual photograph of
this building. If you're not familiar
with this kind of architecture,
so what they would do is they'd make
these bricks out of mud. They'd
essentially cover it with plaster and
then use like a kind of a form of like
whitewash type paint because if you
know, this is made out of mud and if it
gets wet, it's going to collapse. But
because these are mud bricks, so to
speak, underneath here, that's really,
really heavy. And so they need these
like buttressing walls to kind of keep
it in place or the whole thing would
just collapse. So, that's why it has
this very
distinctive architecture. And then
again, just really interesting
perspective of the front with the gate
and then the church behind this, you
know, it's like we're approaching it as
tourists, we're going to go check it out
inside and the little dabs of green in
there and then the clouds make them more
visually interesting. A close-up of the
gate.
And then the rear view. So, just again,
interesting choosing these different
perspectives for the church.
>> [snorts]
>> And these are just three of the
paintings. She actually painted it
several times, but
due to time limitations, I just picked
these three. But there's if you like
this, there's actually several other
works that she did.
It always reminds me of that there's a
great movie if if you've seen it, one of
the early Sidney Poitier movies,
Lilies of the Field. And he's I can't
remember the specific state, it might be
this one, but that's the theme of it.
There's this group of Catholic nuns that
are want to build a chapel and they rope
this guy into helping them build this
impossible chapel. But it has a lot of
this kind of construction in it.
Okay, well, that's cool. Yeah, and that
was a good movie and
and Sidney Poitier won the Academy
Award. Yes.
Yeah, it's always nice to have these
connections with other historical and
cultural things. Let's see, Georgia
O'Keeffe's time in New Mexico, she spent
a significant amount painting skulls.
And I'm not people skulls, animal
skulls, particularly like cow skulls and
stuff. And so here's three examples.
Now, she did
these through much of the early years of
her career in New Mexico. So, we'll look
at these ones and then a little bit
later we'll look at some other ones and
you can kind of compare and contrast it.
Um we were talking before in the earlier
program. So, I think this is the third
time we've done this one,
which is why we're recording it because
we probably won't be repeating anytime
soon. But anyway, we were talking before
about how she used to do these paintings
of these New York skyscrapers,
which were like very vertical. And this
is a very vertical painting because you
have this like white post in the
background
with the skull on it. It's bleached
white, the sun-bleached skull. And it's
really interesting just because of the
jagged edges and the worn surfaces of
the skull. And you know, now walking is
really popular, but it wasn't so much of
a big thing back then, but Georgia
O'Keeffe was really kind of ahead of her
time because she used to like to go for
walks
in the New Mexico landscape where she
was staying and she would find these
objects and bring them back to her home
and studio and then make these fabulous
paintings of them.
This one is also interesting because
red, white, and blue, of course,
the colors of the American flag, so very
kind of patriotic in that regard. Um
I think Also her own
her own take on red and blue.
Yeah, she she creates her own colors.
Like O'Keeffe does that.
Yeah, those aren't the standard like
American flag colors by any means. And I
think for a lot of times in art, if
there's a skull, whether it's an animal
skull or a human skull, it often times
means like death or
you know, the limitations of life and
things like that. But she wasn't really
focused on that. She was just thought
they were just really interesting shapes
and forms.
And she was really kind of just trying
to capture the beauty and the spirit of
the desert. And again, that kind of
contrast with the
white of the skull and the red and the
blue in background.
Weary of life in the metropolis, meaning
New York City, Georgia O'Keeffe began
taking regular retreats to New Mexico in
1929. Her artistic interest shifted from
the buildings of New York to the nature
of New Mexico. So, that's a really
interesting shift because
previously her art was focused more on
urban things.
In this work, O'Keeffe isolates a single
skull, highlighting its jagged edges,
worn surfaces, and bleached color. To
O'Keeffe, such bones represented the
desert's enduring beauty and the
strength of the American spirit, which
is alluded to in the striped background.
In 1949, O'Keeffe settled permanently in
New Mexico where she lived until her
death in 1986.
Really amazing details on the jagged
edges. Oh, was someone going to say
something?
Well, Kim has mentioned that she read a
while ago that she was a very
she was very protective over her skull
collection and considered them elite
objects to own.
Yeah, I mean,
you know, these aren't just random
things that she's finding, but they
become very important to her.
And then, you know, documenting through
her artwork. So, appreciate that
comment.
Here's another one. It's at the Art
Institute of Chicago, Cow's Skull with
Calico Roses. Um so there was a big
drought in 1930, you know, if you kind
of think of like the um
uh you know, the Great Depression and
uh you know, all that kind of stuff. Uh
this drought impacted the Southwest. It
impacted a lot of animals were killed.
And so there were more skulls kind of
just laying around
um more so than normal. Um but again,
kind of this focus on shapes and
textures and really interesting kind of
uh contrast here between the skull and
these Calico Rose flowers, which are
also white.
It was hard to get burial details to go
out and bury all those cows that had
been to die.
>> [laughter]
>> Oh yeah, right exactly.
Um
and then here's what Georgia O'Keeffe
had to say about the skulls. To me, they
are as beautiful as anything I know. To
me, they are strangely more living than
the animals walking around. The bones
seem to cut more sharply to the center
of something that is keenly alive on the
desert, even though it is vast and empty
and untouchable and knows no kindness
with all its beauty.
She's a good writer, too.
Yeah, I mean she has really um that's a
good point. I appreciate you mentioning
it. Yeah, she has really interesting
thoughts and she's really able to
articulate kind of what she's trying to
accomplish. Um Georgia O'Keeffe had a
really strong connection with Chicago.
Um she actually donated this painting to
the museum. Uh and you can see her
standing next to it in her
uh I don't remember the exact year photo
was taken.
It was probably in the '50s.
Yeah, I can see her looking very
'50s-esque.
Um let's see.
Well, just by her age, I'm going by her
age. Wait, she Wait, did she die in the
1960s?
No, 1986. 1980s.
Yeah.
The '80s.
Let's see. In Cow's Skull with Calico
Roses, Georgia O'Keeffe decorated the
skull with artificial flowers. That's
unusual. Um people might not have keyed
in on that. The kind used to adorn
graves in New Mexico, tucked against the
ear and the jaw, the flowers appear less
morbid than simply decorative. A
whimsical addition that relies on the
soft ruffled petals to alleviate the
hard polished severity of the skull. So
kind of interesting contrast between the
flowers and the skull. Um O'Keeffe then
exquisitely exquisitely balanced these
subtle modulations of the white and gray
tones of the skull and flowers with a
bold vertical streak of dark brown that
irregularly bisects the composition.
With the skull positioned against a
muted layered ground in close proximity
to the picture plane, the composition
conveys a sense of the organic yet
abstracted beauty typical of O'Keeffe's
art.
Somebody had had pointed out through the
number of times you see crosses embedded
in her work and you don't think of
I mean, I don't think of her as a
particularly associated with religion of
any type and yet that theme keeps does
keep coming up.
Oh yeah, that's a good point, too, cuz
yeah, I I feel the same exact way that
you do see the crosses quite a bit. So
I'm glad somebody pointed that out. But
yeah, I don't really consider her like a
overly
uh religious uh person, so to speak, at
least not in terms of her artwork. And
yet she incorporates these symbols of
death. As you mentioned, they're used in
funerals. The those flowers are used in
funerals and stuff. So she's got
the there's that relationship with
the permanence and yet impermanence of
life as we know it. So she seems to
relate beyond the dimensions, you know?
Yeah, it'd be a great question to ask
her if she could join our program
tonight before we log off.
Um so again, kind of the focus here on
shapes of the skull and the flower, um
form and the textures of the different
objects and also these really cool
colors. This is at the Los Angeles
County Museum of Art.
And to
position it on that baby blue blankety
looking thing that doesn't necessarily
have a
you know, you can't tell for sure what
it is, but it it it just is a perfect
combination of colors.
Yeah, the colors are really spectacular
in this one with the white and the pink
and the blue and the green.
And again, um you know, her art is so
distinctive. Like how many people can
you think of that make these um animal
skulls? I mean,
and you consider there's been, you know,
hundreds of thousands of artists or
maybe millions of artists over the
course of time. So for someone to stand
out and be so unique
is really quite an accomplishment. Now,
uh you know, we're talking about 1929,
early 1930s, the depression is going on.
Uh here's two famous artworks from
photographers during that time. You
don't really You don't really see that
incorporated in her artwork unless you
want to extrapolate out the ideas of the
um
the skulls.
Um but you know, she's going on kind of
doing her own thing. So uh this is the
Green Mountains in Canada from 1932.
This is a geographical area in Quebec
and this beautiful panoramic landscape.
Um so very different. This is not New
Mexico. Um this is in Canada and Georgia
O'Keeffe actually traveled quite a bit.
And I like this painting a lot. It's
very It's kind of sort of uh
symbolic of a lot of O'Keeffe paintings
in the simplified forms and the
landscape and the beautiful colors, but
it's also very different. The greens and
it's, you know, not a not a New Mexico
kind of thing. So kind of kind of like
O'Keeffe painting, but kind of different
at the same time.
And Robert, your voice keeps
your voice keeps completely
disappearing. I'm not sure if you knew
it and this is a recording. Uh-oh, sorry
about that. Let me
see if I can fix that.
Okay, well thanks. I appreciate that.
Um let's see. Continue on. This is at
the Whitney Museum of American Art. This
is the Mountain, New Mexico, 1931. So
her early New Mexico years.
And again, depicting the natural world
with these beautiful colors.
And yeah, when she gets into these
hills, I mean, to me they feel alive
in ways I can't explain, but they just
flow.
Yeah, I would agree with that as well.
They were just very lively.
It's almost like you can see them
breathing.
Yeah, like there's going to be or
activity taking place. Something
interesting on this one. Notice it's,
you know, the mountains and stuff, but
she does have a little bit of the sky in
the top.
In chat, somebody described this as the
cold cuts painting.
I've had a laugh at that myself.
>> [laughter]
>> It's an Italian sub.
>> [snorts]
>> As as as Patty and I are here
elaborating on all this, you know,
aesthetically stuff.
>> [laughter]
>> The cold cuts painting. Oh yeah, it's
right to the chase.
Deli meat.
Um let's see. Here's another one kind of
from around the same era. Of course
again, we're talking New Mexico.
Now, this one I feel like the hands of
the universe kind of folded in in
peaceful
pose, you know?
I don't know. And I can't get the cold
cuts out of my mind. Kim Kim, can you
get me off on this tangent? Grinders all
around, everybody.
>> I'm going to
after this program's over, I'm going to
go up to the deli and
I'm going to
get some cold cuts.
>> Robert, you said it in New England
style, grinders. I haven't heard that
long, long time. But that's a I'm a New
Englander, born and bred. Yeah.
Northeast.
Even up here they don't say that as much
as they used to. So it's kind of
interesting to hear it. It's like, "Oh
my gosh, that's a word from the past."
Uh let's see. Here's another one of my
favorites. This is at the Art Institute
of Chicago. This is Red Hills with
Flowers from 1937.
Um a really interesting contrast in the
scale because uh you know, flowers are
pretty small. Um hills are very large,
but yet uh the way she's got these
positioned in the painting with the
perspective, uh they seem kind of on par
with each other. So these beautiful
flowers and the mountains in the
background. To me, the the flowers dwarf
the mountain. It really is that
microscope
uh effect. Yeah, the magnification.
Um let's see. Here's a quote from
Georgia O'Keeffe talking about New
Mexico. All the earth's colors
of the painter's palette are out there,
meaning in New Mexico. And I would agree
with that. If just New Mexico is just
such an extraordinary place to um visit
and see. And I just really love this
painting. Um you know, it's a great
depiction of you know, is it a floral
painting or is it a landscape painting
or kind of combination of the two?
Probably.
And great colors.
You know, the composition is pretty
basic. Oh, go ahead, Joan.
Yeah, New Mex over in mountain
over in Taos in that area, uh the you
know, the earth has a reddish tinge and
she just captures that brilliantly.
Yeah, I yeah.
I have to tell you a funny story. So I
grew up in Detroit and when I graduated
from college, I went on this 3 and 1/2
week road trip to the Southwest and I'd
seen like the red dirt like in pictures
and stuff on TV, but I never actually
seen in person. And I was so fascinated
by it that I pulled over the side of the
road and scooped some up in like a uh
uh cup or something
and took it home. I just thought it was
so fascinating. Um but yeah, this has
this really great uh scale of colors,
but yeah, the red's really really
extraordinary.
Um let's see. If you want to learn more
about the Georgia O'Keeffe flower
paintings, we did a whole program um on
those in the abstractions, which is on
our YouTube channel. That was part two.
Um but again, going back to this
painting, just love the kind of the way
the colors complement and contrast one
another with this painting
and the composition. Very cool.
Yeah, just the just the juxtaposition is
is like hypnotic.
Oh yeah, I mean look at these flowers. I
mean I could look at the painting just
like this.
But it just makes it more visually
interesting with the juxtaposition with
the mountains or the hills.
So if you're in Chicago,
there's a lot of great Georgia O'Keeffe
paintings at the museum because she
donated a lot of her artworks to there.
So you should go see this one in person.
It's it's spectacular to see on the
computer but even more so
in person for those of you in Chicago.
Do you know roughly what the scale of it
Robert?
What's that? Do you know roughly the
dimensions of it? It looks like it's
probably a big painting.
Oh yeah, it's like kind of her standard
size. I don't remember the exact
dimensions off the top of my head but
it's not like you know 10 ft wide or
anything
like that.
Um, let's see then back to some more
skull
Oh go ahead. You said she donated
paintings to the
to the Art Museum in Chicago.
I mean she just gave it to
>> actually Yeah, she actually Well, she
studied there as a student when she was
in her early career and then she
actually worked in Chicago as a
commercial artist for a year. So she
really had a long kind of And then
Chicago is actually not far from where
she was born in Wisconsin.
So she had a really long kind of lasting
relationship with Chicago which I think
some people don't realize.
Um, let's see. So yeah, more skull
paintings.
These ones were done a little bit later.
The earlier ones were like 1929 early
1930s. This is at the Brooklyn Museum of
Art in New York. Ram's Head, White
Hollyhocks Hills.
And so you have the skull and this
flower kind of floating so to speak
in the background is the landscape.
And that cross effect.
Yeah, the cross effect. Uh-huh.
And then here's another great one. This
is at the Whitney Museum of American
Art. So a lot of great Georgia O'Keeffe
paintings in New York City as well. This
is called Summer Days from 1936.
In Summer Days Georgia O'Keeffe
suspended an animal skull with several
Southwestern flowers above a barren
desert landscape. The large scale of the
bones and blossoms and their placement
in the sky gave the painting a surreal
quality.
For O'Keeffe the animal skull and
vibrant flowers were symbols of the
cycles of life and death that shaped the
natural world. This composition belongs
to a group of paintings in which the
artist depicted the sun-bleached bones
she brought back east from her summer
sojourns in New Mexico. The deer, horse,
mule, and steer skulls she collected as
one would gather wildflowers became
potent souvenirs of a landscape that had
deeply inspired her. As she explained,
"The bones cut sharply to the center of
something that is keenly alive in the
desert." So just to go back to the
context. So again, Georgia O'Keeffe she
starts visiting New Mexico in 1929. What
happened was she was still living in New
York. So for several years she'd spend
approximately half the year in New
Mexico by herself and then the other
half of the year back in New York City
with her husband Stieglitz. As far as I
know, I don't think he ever went out to
New Mexico
with her. So it was kind of like a
something she would do
on her own. But as the kind of the
caption says here, she's taking
oftentimes these bones back to New York
with her so she can finish the painting.
So at this point in time in her career
she's spending her time
in New York City and half in New Mexico.
You know, I'm going to say it now
because I keep thinking of it every time
Stieglitz comes into this.
If you're interested in a little bit
more of him,
check out
Do you remember which one it is? The
There's more than one Georgia O'Keeffe
program on the YouTube channel, right?
Right now?
Oh yeah, yeah. We Well, we talked about
him a lot in the first one cuz it was
centered around her time in New York
City.
>> Okay, yeah. Because it's just really
interesting. You get an idea of what's
going on historically because the shots
of his studio
contrast so strangely with the modern
art he was real
he was really getting into promoting.
Oh yeah, mhm.
It's that's
>> different than these works. Yeah, and it
Yeah, it's
>> It's it's a weird juxtaposition because
his gallery was very antique-y like
an old type of
European style heavily draped and all
this other stuff. So the contrast with
the modern art is really kind of it
really kind of telegraphs to you like,
"Oh yeah, that's when this was
happening."
Yeah, really stands out. Uh-huh. Yeah. I
know exactly what you mean. Um, let's
see. Here's a close-up of the skull. So
again, um, you know, how many artists do
paintings of these animals and skulls?
Fascinating.
Here's a nice one at the Museum of Fine
Arts Boston.
This mountain in the background is known
as locally as Pedernal and Georgia
O'Keeffe painted on numerous occasions
including this time.
That was her neighbor, right? That
mountain? Yeah, mhm. Yeah, that
She really considered the mountain to be
her neighbor.
And here's one at the Metropolitan
Museum of Art in New York.
From the Far Away Nearby.
That cross effect
it's really mystical.
Oh yeah, yeah, really unique. So again,
combining the bones and the landscape
she really disregards the scale cuz the
you know, it looks like the
compared to the mountain the
the skull seems extremely large which of
course these are pretty large but just
kind of interesting how she has the
floating
juxtaposition so to speak. It's kind of
a She's not really Georgia O'Keeffe is
not really considered a quote unquote
surreal artist but there are kind of
surreal elements to her artwork. Um, and
the thought is that So Georgia O'Keeffe
most of her paintings she titled
herself. And so the thought behind this
one is maybe this is something related
to Stieglitz because
you know, they were still married and
you know, lovers and all that stuff in a
romantic relationship but yet they were
apart for roughly half the year every
year.
And so you know, on the one hand the two
of them are far away but on the other
hand they're nearby. So.
There is a much more spiritual
sensibility to these to the New Mexico
paintings than there is to her like say
her New York period.
Oh yeah, yeah. I would I would agree
with that. But it makes me kind of
wonder is that maybe
because of the setting she's in or maybe
she's getting older. I mean, I don't
know myself. I tend to I think about
stuff more deeply than I did when I was
in my 20s.
Exactly. And so I think it was Kim who
said she
she thinks that she was what they call a
drop-in Catholic. In other words, you
know, not like
insanely devout but
you can
That sort of fits as far as I'm
concerned, you know, especially with the
Spanish background and
the indigenous relationships and all
that sort of thing if you if you know
much about that history.
Oh yeah, no definitely.
What about before we kind of move on
from the skulls? Brad and Joanne any
final thoughts on
these skull paintings?
That's the one I jokingly call a
40-point buck. I mean, that's
I call it the jackalope, Brad.
>> [laughter]
>> And what about you Joanne? Any final
thoughts on the New Mexico skulls before
we
continue on?
Well,
one person said this reminds me of
Rudolph at his best. And yeah, when I
saw this one here, I was thinking of
Rudolph and all the Santa's reindeers
here.
Oh, that's funny. Well, that's why it's
interesting to
get other people's ideas on art and
stuff just because I don't know. People
come up with things I would have never
thought of.
>> [laughter]
>> And yeah, there were pearls around the
skull and the horns.
And yeah, mirror Mimi said there's
almost a Salvador Dali flavor in this
painting. I would agree.
What did you say there were pearls?
Is that what you said? Pearls?
The one on the far right.
No, those aren't pearls.
Yeah, there's pearls. I think that she
added horns to this.
So I think that's actually the base of
of the horn not necessarily pearls.
I don't know. You know, good question. I
never thought of that.
>> Well, the thing the beauty of these
paintings is you can do your own
interpretation. She gives you that
freedom.
Well, yeah.
And I don't know.
So let me go back to the earlier skull
paintings.
So I forgot to do that. So hold on
one moment. There's a lot of ambiguity.
So here were the first ones we saw.
See along if you can barely see it but
if you look at the base of the horn,
horns aren't bones. They're actually
made out of horn and they're not
permanently attached. That's why you see
some broken off and some intact. But you
can see the little place where they
bond onto the skull.
Well, you notice these ones
so different the later ones than the
earlier ones. She's it's more of the you
know,
landscape in the background. Whereas the
earlier ones she wasn't really doing
that as much. It was just more of a
plain as background. So, kind of one way
maybe if you had to identify
um these O'Keeffe paintings as time goes
by. Um let's get back to some
landscapes. So, I love this painting
also. It's at the Milwaukee Art Museum.
>> fabulous. Great art collection. It's
called the Cliff Chimneys
uh from 1938. And a really great uh
vertical view, which is kind of unusual
because you know, it's this isn't unique
to Georgia O'Keeffe, but usually
landscape paintings are horizontal. Um
so, just the fact that she's doing this
vertical thing
is really cool. And I love the shapes
and the colors in this one including all
the green. Uh so, really fabulous.
And the vertical emphasizes that
chimney. You know, that I
>> Yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, much more so than if it was a
horizontal. I mean, I'm not complaining.
I can see why she made
a vertical painting. But uh landscape
paintings 90% of the time probably are
uh usually horizontal.
>> [snorts]
>> I just have that there's one where she's
holding on to a canvas, one photo we
have of her. Um and I just picture her
picking up a blank canvas knowing
exactly what she's about to put on it.
She just seems like that kind of a
painter to me.
Yeah, decisive. Yes.
And then this one is at the Art
Institute of Chicago.
Uh Oh, hold on. Hold on for 1 second. I
have to speak something on my computer.
Um this one the I remember the first
time I saw this. I kind of had to look
at it like what exactly is this?
Um [laughter]
because like
the semi abstraction or abstract quality
of it. Um let's see.
You can actually even see it in one
sense as a like a misshapen thumb with a
red painted nail. It just
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, well yeah, that's kind of what I
meant like Yeah.
>> a toe or something or what is
>> [laughter]
>> What exactly is that?
A toe is good, too. Yeah.
What it's What it is that so
Oh, go ahead.
>> sitting there, you know, it's like oh,
what?
So, if you haven't figured out, it's
actually a rock that's on top of another
rock. So, the on the top part, the
darker color,
um this is a rock.
And then it's on top of another rock.
And then of course, you have this part
of this um jaw bone down here. So, or
teeth. So, there you go. Pink rocks and
teeth. But what if But the first time I
saw this painting, I didn't see the um
title. The title wasn't available. So,
what exactly is that? Um but again,
another great artwork at the Art
Institute of Chicago.
Georgia O'Keeffe was fascinated by the
animal bones weathered and worn that she
found in the desert in New Mexico. In
Red and Pink Rocks and Teeth, she
presented a jaw bone alongside two
stacked rocks that appear both
monumental and intermediate. Uh the
smooth rounded forms of the red and pink
rocks appear in enigmatic relation to
one another as the red pebble appears to
recede from the picture plane even
though it must be perched on top of the
pink stone. Their abstracted forms and
warm colors contrast sharply with the
bleached angular teeth and hard cracked
appearance of the jaw bone and together
construct a modern I'm not even sure how
you pronounce that. Um
that uh questions the nature
representation and perception. So, I
guess my my thought was like how would
you even come up with the idea for this?
Like you know, you got a this part of a
jaw bone and some rocks and like oh, I
think I'll put it together like this. I
mean, cuz you know, she had to put this
composition together. It wasn't you
know, found in nature like this. So, how
did she do that?
Oh, trompe l'oeil. That's what Yeah.
That's how I think that's how you
pronounce it. Trompe l'oeil.
Think so.
Yeah, it's not really something you
associate with her based on like her
life's work. So, it really pops out that
it's like wait, this is Georgia
O'Keeffe, too?
Mhm.
And it is a really interesting contrast
between these jagged shapes um of the
teeth and the rounded
Oh, here's a good question. Catherine
says, "What does that mean?" Um I don't
know if she's referring to the
the French word or this painting. I'm
not I'm not sure what the painting
means.
It means fool the eye.
Trick the eye.
Oh, I see. Oh, okay.
Our word for the day.
Use that when you guys go into
your job tomorrow or next time you're
mingling with people.
Um let's see.
And then here's one from the Museum of
Fine Arts, Houston. Well, look at the
fabulous red colors here. This is Red
Hill and White Shell from 1938. Um
interestingly enough, so these shells
aren't from New Mexico. We were kind of
having
debate about this the last time we had
this
uh program. But wow, look at these
fabulous colors. And again, these great
shapes and the simplified forms and the
magnification of the shell.
But I believe I read somewhere This is a
long time ago, but these kinds of shells
are found in all sorts of places and all
kinds of archaeological digs.
I think you're right, but they figured
out that this particular one is a
northern moon sea snail because there's
people that are experts on shells. And
it Well, and I think personally, too, is
you know, like the some shells are kind
of like uh
you know, common forms.
Um
>> That's what I was going to say. But
again, these are found objects. Yeah. I
meant the form, not the not the uh
specific shell. Yeah. Mhm. Yeah, the
kind of the generic shape. Um but these
particular um
northern moon sea snails
uh from Atlantic beaches. So, kind of
interesting that she would combine uh
something from the East Coast with
something from New Mexico. She had
pretty strong firm roots in just a in a
lot of places.
And this is not the shell that's in the
painting, but just a shell show you what
it would look like.
But Her painting The painting looks
angry to me. To me. Especially
>> So, yeah.
>> red shell. That looks so realistic.
Yeah, it just looks like the eye of
judgment is focusing on me.
>> Oh, I see.
>> [laughter]
>> With the red in the background. That
That's my interpretation.
Now, what about this um this other one,
which is kind of similar, but a little
bit different? Do you feel the same way
about that one?
This one's even more vibrant.
So, the contrast it is is intense. But I
I love the contrast, so.
Oh, yeah. They're great.
>> have put them side by side. I didn't
think about about that.
Yeah, the second one I think is like I
don't know. It's like I can feel a
little pulse in my blood pressure kind
of looking at
It's It's very vibrant. It's excitement,
I think. And then it says guilty
conscience.
>> [laughter]
>> Look at the horizon line in this. It's
not only a red mountain coming up, but
you got red clouds up above. It's like a
sunrise
>> a good point. Yeah, like sunrise kind of
thing.
Kim says, "I think the contrast makes
the shells glow."
Yeah.
And then um Beth says, "What media did
she use?" So, most of these almost all
of her paintings were oil paintings. Um
she did do some watercolors and things
like that. But
I think most of the paintings in this um
program are oil paintings.
There's actually
other than snail, I mean, there's
actually a name for this shell shape. Um
that's what I mean about I'm remembering
from this article and I can't remember
what the name is, but it's a very common
thing. It shows up all over the world in
all kinds of places, this particular
type of shell. I don't know what you're
talking about because we discussed it in
um Earth Science freshman year of
college. But I don't remember that far
back.
It seems like a long time ago, yes, that
I read about it. Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> Um let's see. So,
um this big giant mountain that was next
to where Georgia O'Keeffe lived, uh it's
known as the Pedernal. That's the like
the local name of it. Uh and this is a
view of it from Georgia O'Keeffe's home.
So, her home She lived in a few
different places um or well, initially
when she was just going out there like
for vacation, so to speak, she was
living in different place. But then even
um when she got more roots, she stayed
in a few different place. But this is uh
one of the more famous places is Ghost
Ranch. And so, this is the view of this
mountain, uh which is really
spectacular, which is why people should
go um check out this site. And then here
it is like kind of I
hesitate to call this area like the
courtyard, so to speak, of her um uh
setup here. But you can see the
beautiful mountain in the background.
So, she was really fascinated by this uh
mountain range and the the Pedernal
height part um in particular because she
made numerous paintings. You actually
already seen it a couple times um in
some of the earlier works. And then man,
how would you love to wake up to this
view? This is the um view from Georgia
O'Keeffe's bedroom at this really cool
uh intersection of the windows here in
the corner. So, that she had this great
uh views. I mean, imagine opening up
your curtains in the morning to see that
or or waking up to that or going to
sleep to that. Uh really spectacular. Um
but she ends up doing all these
different paintings of this. So, these
are just a few examples. Um but she
actually did like dozens of paintings of
this mountain. And again, kind of
interesting that she took um
kind of different approaches. Like these
two, the compositions kind of similar,
but the colors are very different. Uh
and then over here, this one, the
composition's very different. The
mountain's down here in the bottom and
you have all this uh sky in the
background and of course the photo from
kind of more modern times.
Yeah, the upper right one looks almost
sunsetish, but I don't know you know,
obviously I wouldn't know.
Yeah.
Um, let's see. So this is at the Georgia
O'Keeffe Museum in Santa Fe
Joanne was talking about earlier and the
name of this
location is the Cerro Pedernal or Flint
Hill in English.
And it's a mesa which you maybe heard
that term but don't know what that
means. It's a flat-topped elevation.
This particular elevation is pretty
high, 9,866
ft.
And she really felt attached to this um
location. She actually called it my
private mountain even though she didn't
actually own the mountain, but she just
felt such a strong connection to this
particular place.
And this is another painting at the
Georgia O'Keeffe Museum in Santa Fe.
There we go. I love our audiences. Greg
says those are nautilus shells, exactly.
>> [laughter]
>> Oh, there you go. All right, thanks
Greg. Appreciate the assistance there.
Good job. I knew there was a categorical
name for them. I just couldn't come up
with it. And Catherine
Catherine says what a contrast to New
York or Chicago.
Yeah, and that's what I mean.
There's a sense of place about all of
her different periods.
Yeah, uh-huh. Yeah, exactly. Um
Yeah, and Susan talked about the
Fibonacci spiral,
you know, geo- geometric shape based on
a numeric sequence. Yeah, that that I
knew cuz that occurs over and over again
in nature. I was just trying to think of
the genus or whatever you call it of
that type of shell. I knew there was a
categorical name for them. I just
couldn't think of it.
And then if you want to go visit Georgia
O'Keeffe's gravesite and pay your
respects, but you can't really do it
because
she's not buried in a particular place.
So she was cremated, but she liked this
mountain so much her ashes were actually
scattered here. Now interestingly enough
Stieglitz, who was her husband,
his ashes are in a separate place. So
that's a little unusual. He really felt
connected to Lake George and so his
ashes are scattered there. So kind of
you know,
whatever they're they're in different
places, but maybe together in some other
some other way. But again, painting from
1945 and then here they are
in full view. So wow, look at that.
Great colors and again the simplified
forms.
Whoops.
And here's another view.
Annette said she had the ability to
portray that any one thing has many
faces. Yeah, that's a great way to put
it Annette cuz yeah, I mean these are
the same subject but different pieces.
>> going to read Annette's because I think
that's a great line. She did have the
ability and again talking about the
ashes and his are here and his are here
and hers are there.
She does seem to have like a
comprehensive sense of before life, life
and after life and but it's not like
hitting you over the head with it. She
just blends it.
Yeah, it's not forcing you on it, but I
mean it you know at this point in time
she is what 58 years old and you know
back that that era in history and that
would have been you know kind of a
little bit older than it is today cuz
not that many people made it to 58 back
then.
Um, let's see. So yeah, thanks Annette.
I like that. She said she had the
ability to portray that any one thing
has many faces. Yeah.
Um, now so in the earlier program in
part one we were talking about and some
people don't know about these works that
Georgia O'Keeffe did when she was living
in New York, but she's doing all these
cityscapes and skyscrapers and all this
stuff. And I mean if you look at these
paintings
uh and then contrast them with these,
it's like wow, what a what a transition.
So it would have been interesting if she
never would have went out to New Mexico,
if she would have stayed in New York, if
she just would have continued making
paintings like this or similar um for
their whole career, but you know, she
goes off on this different trajectory so
to speak um when she starts going out in
New Mexico and really has a big impact
on her both personally and
professionally. So really kind of
striking in that regard.
Her Wisconsin and
>> The light in the New York paintings is
very different from the light in her New
Mexico paintings.
As the New York ones is kind of like you
know, the strobe lights, Broadway
lights, artificial light.
Yeah. What was that you were going to
say Peggy? I was just going to say her
her Wisconsin and Virginia works too of
are much more pastoral than either of
these others.
Yeah, they're like a whole separate kind
of thing. Yeah, pastoral and domestic.
Oh, here you go. Carolyn giving us the
the general shell shapes. You got
conical,
elongated, and depressed.
Wow.
Um, let's see. And then you know, okay,
so what's going on in the world this
time? Well, World War II is you know,
raging in early 1940s in New Mexico per
se, but you know, you really don't see
that creeping up in her artwork and
that would be another interesting thing
to ask her about like it doesn't seem
like it really impacted her all that
much. She's just kind of like out in her
own little world, but you know, that
being said this part of New Mexico is
kind of a long ways from
you know, the rest of civilization so to
speak. So maybe a little bit isolated in
that regard. As we discussed in one of
the earlier iterations of this program,
she was what? 50 miles from Los Alamos?
Yeah.
Well, a little bit further than that,
but yeah, I mean in the same state. Yes,
that's
ironic there.
Yes, another thing she was friends with
Anita Pollitzer
and at that time Anita Pollitzer and
Alice Paul, who was
were trying to get Jewish refugees in
Switzerland to come off to America
very very quickly.
And yeah, I don't want to digress.
But yeah, Alice Paul lived in
Switzerland in the 1930s
and you know, she helped Jewish refugees
get visas and she called Anita Pollitzer
cuz Pollitzer had a lot of contacts in
New York.
And you know, Georgia O'Keeffe was
corresponding with Anita.
So Georgia knew people who were right in
the thick of all those problems.
And um but yeah, but at the you know,
the same time kind of you know, far away
from
you know, all the stuff that's taking
place and a little bit isolated in that
regard. So
If if this if this were my bedroom, I
would like lose a lot of sleep being
afraid I wouldn't awake in the morning
early enough to see this view.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, anticipation can get in my way
sometimes.
>> [laughter]
>> If this was my bedroom, I would have to
get a work remote job cuz I would never
want to leave home. Exactly. That's what
I mean. I would be awake all night being
hopefully I wouldn't oversleep through
the morning into the morning.
Well, yeah, reminds me Sedona is
Sedona, Arizona is a lot like New
Mexico.
You know, with the red rocks and I
remember I stayed in the hotel that had
a view similar to this and I just didn't
want to leave.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, I think I need to print this out
and hang it on my wall so I can kind of
pretend it's
>> [laughter]
>> Um, let's see. All right, continue on
and then it's back to some more
landscapes. So again,
just she was really fascinated by the
area in and around where she was living
and doing all these different depictions
of it. This is a painting at the
Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York.
Pink and yellow cliffs from 1940.
Interesting, you got the
bottom, the vegetation. So it's almost
like there's three planes here, the the
cliffs take up most of the plane, but if
you look closely,
you know, of course you can see the
greenery down at the bottom and if you
look even closer,
you know, a little hint of sky
up here on the top. So that's really
interesting touch. What's that Peggy? It
reminds me of
I don't even know if they still have
this, but they used to call it
Neapolitan ice cream and when you would
open it
have the
>> [laughter]
>> chocolate, vanilla, and strawberry.
Exactly.
>> Yes, we're dating ourselves.
Do they still make that stuff? That's
what I mean. I don't even know.
I think they still have
three Braum's is a good
>> [laughter]
>> Um, but yeah, but unlike Neapolitan, you
got this one flavor that's taking up
most of the ice cream tub.
But there is that sense of layering, you
know, that's what I was getting at.
>> Yeah, layering. Um, this is another one
the artist did Chicago Red Hills of
Flowers from 1940. This is an unusual
one a little bit in the sense that it's
a horizontal, but it's really a long and
narrow horizontal. And again, just she
was always really inspired by these
landscapes. The places you can go on a
horse here always astonished me. The
most exciting was being on top of a
ridge of red hills and seeing the blue
flat-topped mountains above them. It was
very good.
Kim says having grown up in New York
City, that amount of open land would
scare me to death.
>> [laughter]
>> Who knows what's out there.
Well,
here's a here's a painting that's
getting someone thinking about pastrami
and Swiss. Exactly. Yeah, I think that's
a Neapolitan one. Just depends on your
appetite, I guess.
>> [laughter]
>> Getting hungry. Um, let's see. She
seemed to be able to absorb the
atmosphere wherever she was, hence the
incredible difference in the attitude in
her paintings. Yeah, I would agree with
that.
Yeah, which um
It's like what you took a white canvas.
She already knew what was going to go on
it.
She seems that decisive to me.
Yeah, and to your point earlier, Patty,
that you know, she's doing all these
diverse types of things in all these
different places that she's at in these
different phases of her life. It's not
the same thing over and over again.
Right. It's like whatever
>> I think she That's what happened That's
what comes onto the canvas.
Yeah, she could capture the essence of
New York, of New Mexico, Wisconsin.
And then let's Oh, someone asked a
question, did she sketch before she
painted? Yes, some artists will sketch
things out and then make the paintings,
but she didn't really do much of that.
She oftentimes just started painting
directly on the canvas, which to go back
to Patty's point earlier is pretty
amazing cuz it She does seem like a very
decisive uh
artist. This one is at a great museum
that's not far from where Joanne and I
live. Uh Joanne and Garland
>> Yes. uh myself in Fort Worth at Amon
Carter Museum of American Art. This is
Dark Mesa with Pink Sky.
>> [laughter]
>> The Amon Carter Museum actually has the
most Georgia O'Keeffe paintings
of any museum in the state of Texas,
much to the chagrin of the Dallas Museum
of Art and the Museum [laughter] of Fine
Arts, Houston.
Uh the former director of the Amon
Carter Museum uh was actually in a
unfriendly terms with Georgia O'Keeffe.
Um
And so that's one reason why they have a
great collection of artworks there.
And then here's one at the Smithsonian
Hirshhorn Museum, which is the modern
art museum of the Smithsonian. Black
Hills with Cedar from 1941.
That is one of my favorite museums, the
Hirshhorn. Yeah. Oh, yeah? Okay, that is
a really cool museum. Uh if you get a
chance to right on the National Mall,
features modern and contemporary art.
Yeah, it's fascinating. Yeah.
I'm sorry, Joanne.
No, I just said it was fascinating.
Yeah.
And then Philadelphia Museum of Art
>> of Georgia O'Keeffe's, I just think of
anger. That's just me.
Well, what about these ones that are
kind of orangish red? Like this one.
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> I just love the nuance.
>> the nuance.
Yeah.
I mean, look at that mountain in the
background. When you get to the far back
Yeah. Yeah, and then the bones. This has
a lot of perspective in it.
I mean, this takes you back and back and
back into this painting.
Mhm.
Yeah, it's got a lot of depth.
Yeah.
And then here's one at the Cleveland
Museum of Art. Cliffs, Neon, Abiquiu,
Dry Waterfall, 1942. So, uh notice the
multicolored cliffs here. Um you know,
she really does a great job of kind of
uh capturing all these different shades
and tones of
uh of the geographic forms that she's
depicting and then putting a little bit
of the vegetation in here as well. And
then of course the sky. So, we've seen
that kind of over and over again.
This one also reminds me of that What is
it? Frozen? Is that the movie that all
the kids love to sing all those songs?
>> Yeah. That that This reminds me of them.
Oh, yeah?
And look, there's a cross right there.
Oh, yeah, yeah. Good point. Good
observation.
And here's one at the Cincinnati Art
Museum. My Backyard. Well, imagine
having a backyard like this. Uh this
beautiful landscape.
Was it Kim that said it's that they grew
up in New York City? This Yeah.
My backyard. Oh my god.
>> [laughter]
>> Georgia O'Keeffe's title for this
picture, My Backyard, is both an ironic
and affectionate commentary on the
subject. While the image defies the
stereotype of the typical suburban
backyard that was going on in mid-1900s,
uh the title refers to the artist's
intense personal connection to the space
she experienced every day. So, I can't
stress that enough how strongly um
connected she felt with this place. It
really carries over into her art. Uh the
painting is composed of horizontal bands
with the cooler tones at the top and
bottom framing the warmer passages in
the middle. We've kind of seen those
color bands
um
throughout the program tonight. By the
time O'Keeffe created this painting, she
had an established a reputation as a
pioneering figure of American modernism
or early non-representational
work in her distinctive semi-abstract
paintings of natural objects, landscape
and architecture. Her intention, she
noted, was to make people truly look at
nature.
I like that. That's for me. Yeah, that's
What's that, Patty?
Semi-abstract is a good expres- is a
good
uh expression for that.
Oh, yeah. Mhm. And were you going to say
something, Joanne?
Uh no. I was just agreeing. Okay.
All right, that's good.
Um let's see.
It's not so abstract as to appear
disconnected from nature, but it's also
nature in a glorified way.
Yeah, it's not
definitely not photographic like either.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's It's her take. Yeah,
semi-abstract.
>> highly individualistic take on nature.
Yeah, good point. Her take. Um let's
see. And then okay, so here's some back
to some bones again. Now, notice these
are very different than the ones we saw
before. Um she's focusing on these blue
background. She's not really showing the
whole object. She's showing a portion of
it. Uh she's really zooming in.
And so at the Indianapolis Museum of
Art, 1943. And focus here on the shapes
and the textures and the colors.
1943 and 1947, Georgia O'Keeffe painted
a series of works in which sun-bleached
animal bones
prominently situated within the natural
environment of the Southwest. The bones
were usually pictured in their entirety
or in magnified detail. Here in the
abstract variation, she draws attention
to the blue sky seen through empty
sockets.
Uh the work demonstrates O'Keeffe's
ability to present what the writer Jean
Toomer described as  the universe
through the portal of a bone. {end
quote}
And you know, if you look at this long
with the arrangement of colors, all of a
sudden you'll see a sailboat.
That's [laughter] cool.
Um well, let me do this. Let me go back
to look at these other skull ones.
>> [laughter]
>> I live next to the ocean. So, I guess
that's what I'm trying to say. It's
like, okay, it could be New Mexican
desert, but it can also be the Atlantic.
>> [laughter]
>> So, remember we saw these gives you that
freedom.
Yeah, she gives you that freedom. That's
the connect- that sense of eternity and
eternal connection that that comes
through in a lot of these paintings.
Mhm.
So, look at these skulls and you can
kind of see some differences between the
time she painted them. And then maybe if
you go to an art museum by your house or
on a vacation or something, you'll see
one like, oh, that's kind of from such
and such era. So, these ones um it's
usually the full skull and the
background is kind of like a abstract
kind of like made-up background. And
then you fast forward to kind of the
next phase.
She did these. Um which again, usually
it's the full skull. Um but oftentimes
these ones it's the landscape in the
background like it's been juxtaposed
um over the natural world. So, so that's
a little bit different than what we saw
a few seconds ago. And then now you fast
forward to these next set.
Hold on a second.
The first one The first series there's
almost like an early Americana
sensibility to them.
And then you got these. So, again,
maybe you'll visit a art museum by your
home or on a trip and you can look at
one of these skull paintings like, oh,
okay, yeah, yeah, yeah. Um so, you know,
they're very distinctive. They're not
all the same uh depending on the time
she painted them. And they're ethereal.
There's something ethereal about them.
Oh, that's a good word, Patty. Thank
you.
Brad, what do you think? Any Any chime
in on these skulls? The comments, these
skulls are very impressive.
Which her works were
incredible anyway, but these looking
through the sockets
up on the on the far right, it almost
looks like the interior of one of the
modern spacecraft. Exactly.
And the These are pelvises, by the way,
not skulls. These These this series
here. Oh, yeah. Thank you. Appreciate
that.
Yeah.
And in some of the skulls, you see
intimate anatomy of of sinuses and
things that you normally wouldn't see.
Right.
And the pelvis, by the way, that's the
core of the body That's called the core.
So, Yeah. Yeah.
And I like your sail sailboat analogy,
Patty.
Well, it's just as I'm staring at it,
that's kind of what it turned into by
itself. I mean, I It wasn't like I was
thinking about it. It just sort of like,
oh, looks like a sailboat.
Even the way she paints the shadow in on
the bone is is like adds that effect.
What planet are we looking at?
That looks like the moon.
It does look
>> Yeah, I was just think- I was thinking
the same thing.
Oh, yeah, or maybe a lake or I don't
know. It could be a lot of different
things.
And almost the way the hip socket goes,
it almost looks like an eye.
Well, yeah.
It as you zero into different parts of
the of the painting. There's so much
possibility in her painting. It's like
which part am I do I want to look at the
most? And you it's almost like you don't
have a choice. It just keeps coming at
you. Keeps feeding you. Yeah. What do
you want to focus on?
>> her genius.
Yeah.
And see, this is the Butler Institute of
American Art in Youngstown, Ohio. This
is Cottonwood 3. Georgia O'Keeffe
oftentimes made a painting
like different versions of the same
thing. So, Cottonwood 1, Cottonwood 2,
this is Cottonwood 3 from 1944.
And then, I really like this one a lot
um as well. The Cleveland Museum of Art.
Dead tree
with pink hill, 1945. So, this is a
cottonwood tree that has seen better
days. But, you know, you don't really
see people doing
depictions of dead trees.
Dead tree.
>> What's that? It's in your face. Dead
tree.
>> The most beautiful dead tree.
I mean, like she was going to come to me
like, "Hey, I'm I'm going to make this
painting of this dead tree in front of
this hill." I'd be like, "Oh, okay.
Yeah, sure. Whatever." But, I don't I
actually like this painting a lot.
That's a saying.
>> I think this might be my favorite
painting of a dead tree that I've ever
seen. What about you guys?
The the stuff There really isn't an
ethereal sense to whatever it is I mean,
whatever her vision is, there's
something ethereal about it. They're
cottonwood yeah. They're cottonwood
trees. And if you look at this dead
tree, the branches have these things
look like cotton balls.
Or spun cotton.
wood trees that spread throughout the
New Mexico landscape provided subjects
for several Georgia O'Keeffe's paintings
including this example. Although no
longer living,
the just a cottonwood scene here is
framed against a distant double-peaked
landmass in near symmetry. Under optimal
environment conditions, cottonwood trees
can live up to 400 years. Wow. Wow.
Yeah.
So, imagine when this one first
sprouted. It must could have been
potentially
a long time before 1945.
And again, what my eyes do with this and
this goes back to that trompe l'oeil
thing.
Um
my eyes go back and forth between seeing
this as a little scrubby tree behind two
massive hills or in front of two massive
hills. And other times, it's like a
great big tree.
Mhm. Does that make sense? I don't I
can't explain
>> no. I I see the same thing now that you
mention it.
I think the tree is beautiful. It is.
Yeah.
Yeah, beauty in the death of the tree.
Even though the tree's dead, it's still
beautiful. Well, and she's got to
juxtapose with this living vegetation.
So, it's like it's really underscoring
the whole idea.
But, there's still hope.
>> [laughter]
>> And what this was created in 1945?
Mhm.
Yeah, I can't resist putting my own
interpretation.
What's that?
>> end of the war,
uh atom bomb, all that sort of thing.
Exactly. As soon as you said that's
where you were going. Amazing.
>> You never know. Yeah, that tree got too
close a look at the uh
side of the first explosion.
And yes, and that's put it in uh cuz I
keep saying ethereal and it says she has
the unique ability to bridge the
distance between life and death.
Great way to put it, Anette.
Yeah. And Chris said, "Did she make any
sculptures? The abstract public
paintings seem to be moving in that
direction."
Oh, she did make some sculptures um
later in her career. I didn't include
any in the program though, but yeah, she
did kind of dabble with that a little
bit later in her career. There's another
one from the Hirshhorn in Washington,
D.C. This is Goat's Horn with red.
Ooh. Yeah.
Couple couple more comments that I think
really capture this um what we've been
talking about. Um
let's see. Anette says again, it would
be overwhelmingly beautiful to go
through life the way she saw it. And
Kathleen says, "Dead but fully in
bloom." Great great
>> Yeah. Yeah.
capture of of the sensibility. Yeah.
And then, eventually Alfred Stieglitz
passed away. So, from 1929 to 1946,
Georgia O'Keeffe was traveling back and
forth spending approximately half the
year in New Mexico
by herself and with friends and stuff.
And the other half of the year
in New York City with her husband. But,
eventually he passed away. And so, then
she goes back to New York and she spends
time there kind of settling his estate
and kind of
you know, doing administrative stuff.
And then afterwards though, she moves to
New Mexico and she pretty much stays
there full-time
for the rest of her life. So, 1946.
And this is an interesting painting. I
don't know if you're reading too much
into this, but you know, this is around
the time her husband passed away. And
this is at the beautiful painting is at
the National Gallery of Art in
Washington, D.C. This is a blackbird
with snow-covered red hills.
Is that related to her husband passing
away? I don't know, but it's interesting
painting nonetheless.
The lines of of the bird are just
extraordinary.
Yeah, really amazing. Yeah, they're
beautiful.
There's no question that bird is in
flight.
Oh, yeah.
Um and then this is the view uh near
where she was living. And interestingly
enough, she painted it different times.
Um so, this is kind of a photo kind of
not exactly when Georgia O'Keeffe was
living there, but kind of close
proximity. And then two different views
of the same setting.
Uh let's see. And here's Georgia
O'Keeffe talking about her
home. "Two walls of my room in the
Abiquiu house are glass. And from one
window, I see the road towards Española,
Santa Fe, and the world." So, this is
the road that she would take to get out
to Santa Fe. Uh
road that people would take to come see
her.
The juxtaposition of the photo with the
two paintings is
it's like there's no gap between them.
One's a black and white photo. The other
two are her expression of that view. And
there's no
there's no alienation among the three.
They all look like the same thing.
Yeah, they're all kind of similar even
though they're very different.
Yeah, so it's it's her sensibility
overlaid on her environment.
Um let's see.
This is called Mesa and Road East. It's
from 1952. And again, beautiful uh New
Mexico landscape.
I wonder, did many people
visit Georgia O'Keeffe at her house in
New Mexico?
Oh, um sometimes. I mean, she wasn't
known to throw like, you know, wild
parties or anything.
>> [laughter]
>> But, I mean, she did get a fair number
of visitors or sometimes she would often
go see other people.
And then, Mesa and Road East number two.
Also from 1952.
And again, there's the mountain and the
road.
And the first painting.
I feel like any minute a car is going to
come cruising down the road.
Exactly. It's [laughter] very desolate.
There's
There's no alienation between the real
photo of the landscape and her paintings
of the landscape, but it Yeah. Actually,
see that little shape down at the bottom
of the mountain? That Is that Could that
be a car or is that supposed to be a
bush? I can't see.
>> know.
I keep waiting for
>> could be a car. I know. A little bitty.
Keep waiting for a RV or a Harley or
something. Yeah. Yeah, I think I think
it's a shrub, but just you know, it just
sort of looks like it could be a car.
And then,
what did Georgia O'Keeffe do for fun
when she wasn't painting? Well, she
loved to travel. You might not realize
Georgia O'Keeffe was a world traveler.
It was one of her favorite things to do.
She visited many, many countries,
traveled all over the US. I mean, she
was, you know, based in New Mexico for
uh much of her life, but she liked to
travel. And so, kind of interesting to
go see her depictions of different
places.
So, here's her take on Hawaii. This is a
waterfall.
So, she visited Hawaii,
make but a few paintings there.
This is at the Baltimore Museum of Art.
>> traveled in the days when people dressed
up when they went to the airport.
Yeah, it was a different was a different
era back then um traveling. You know,
and it was not it was not as common, but
it wasn't as of thing like it is now.
Come fly with me.
>> Yeah, those white Look at those white
gloves and
that wicker basket suitcase.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah. Men wearing suits, ties.
Um, let's see.
And then, how about this? Going off to
Peru.
Wow.
1957.
Yeah, that's stunning.
That is so clearly Machu Picchu, and yet
it's a painting of Machu
>> [laughter]
>> and an impressionistic type painting.
It's amazing.
And then,
>> I would have sensed it very quickly it
was in O'Keeffe.
Here's Mount Fuji.
>> Japan.
So, I don't I don't normally associate
Georgia O'Keeffe with Japan, but she did
go visit there and make quite a few
paintings while she was there. So, you
know, of course she's Georgia O'Keeffe,
not like she's going to go to Japan and
you know, not take a
some paint stuff with her.
But, it's also like she's in some on
some level she's picturing her neighbor,
the Pedernal.
Mhm. Oh, yeah, that's a good point. I
didn't think about that. Yeah, you're
right.
Yeah, this Mount Fuji is fascinating.
I suppose she stayed there long enough
to get a full view of Mount Fuji.
Yeah, I think so because she made more
than one painting of it.
And then, here's the Grand Canyon.
The Colorado where she actually went
white water rafting down the Colorado
River.
Now, is the piece
at the right versus Grand Canyon
experience the Colorado River by raft?
Is that Did they just Is that like an
advertising poster? Oh, um, yeah, so she
didn't make She didn't The artworks on
the right, she didn't make those. I was
just kind of give you the feel for where
she was at. So, this is like a vintage
like travel poster. Um, but this is the
painting that she made and it I just
thought it was interesting because the
poster which she didn't make and the
painting that she did make, they're
pretty consistent as far as like the
look um, so to speak. But then also too,
you know, the travel posters try to
entice people to come visit and so it
does have people in the artwork, but yet
hers there is no It's just strictly 100%
nature. So, kind of interesting
uh comparison and contrast. But no, she
did not make the artwork on the right
just for comparison purposes.
And as much as her paintings are
impressionistic, this
this particular one to me, the first
thought that came into my mind was LSD.
Oh, yeah.
Well, the way the colors and the flow
the flow. So, there's no water in her
painting of it and yet
it's it flows like water. And yet,
painting canyon walls. It's just
I don't I can't explain it, but she had
some kind of a vision that to me seems
magical.
Mhm. 65, that would be the time, Patty.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah, yeah. Good point, Brad.
Again, I wasn't really thinking and and
there's nothing There's no personal
experience involved. It's just that's
the kind of
thing that was happening in in people
the way people would describe these
trips.
Um, yeah, it it it's there's some kind
of ethereal
sense about her that
is impossible to
Well, look at her age, too. I mean,
she's 78 years old and she's going
rafting down the Colorado River.
>> [laughter]
>> You know, and and 78 in 1965 would be a
lot older than 78 today. I mean, that'd
be incredible for some I mean, I hope
I'm
Colorado River rafting at the age of 78
myself.
Um, Well, the nice thing about I reached
that point where it seems like travel
the seems like more of an effort than
than
the the interruption would would grant.
And um, so but the nice thing is I don't
miss it. It's like that it's sort of the
natural flow of my life and that's what
I picture Georgia O'Keeffe. She flows
with life.
Uh-huh.
It's like she wouldn't have been
painting about poor me, I can't go on a
Colorado River trip. She just flows with
what's happening.
Yeah, she just rolls with it. Yeah. Um,
well, she is getting up there in years
and this it's um, she did continue on
painting a little later on in life as
she can imagine she started to have some
health issues, but this is like her last
major, you know, big painting so to
speak. It's called The Beyond and it was
done in 1972. She's 85 years old. And I
mean, think about all the things that
changed in the world and in America and
in her life between 1887 1972. I mean,
that in and of itself is pretty
incredible.
That was one big century, yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> From the Gilded Age to the whatever you
call 1980s.
>> Yeah, the Space Age.
Oh, the disco right? She
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, oh, yeah, yeah.
>> [snorts]
>> I don't
I don't associate Georgia O'Keeffe with
disco.
>> [laughter]
>> I don't associate a lot of things with
disco as it turns out.
But yeah, so this is her last major
painting.
Again, go to the title The Beyond.
She came up with that herself. You kind
of got to wonder, you know, probably
starting to think about not going to be
around for forever with thing, but I
really like this painting a lot. This
pretty abstract and it's the colors and
the bands and all that kind of stuff.
Yeah, and that again is capturing a lot
of this. I don't think she feared aging
or death because her work embraces the
beauty of both. I I agree. That's what I
mean by ethereal. I don't know if that's
what ethereal means, but No, that's a
good point, Annette. I like that. Um,
thanks. Appreciate that.
And let's see. So, yeah, this is our
four-part program on Georgia O'Keeffe.
Uh, part one we talked about her early
New York years. If you want to watch
that, it's on YouTube. Um, I posted the
link in the chat. I'll do it again and
that was also in the um, the email that
had the Zoom link for tonight. Uh, part
two was Georgia O'Keeffe flowers and
abstractions. It's also on YouTube. Um,
this particular program which we're
doing today, we're recording it. So, if
you want to watch it again,
um, or if you joined us late or you know
anyone else would like to see it, um,
I'll post it. Probably won't be able to
get a chance to do that though for a few
days, maybe like this weekend. So, it's
not going to be up for a few days. Just
be patient, it'll be there soon. I'll
try and send an email when it's posted.
And then, part four, which we don't have
a date yet,
we'll talk about Georgia O'Keeffe's life
in New Mexico in particular, her home
and studio.
Go check that out. Um, let's see. If you
want to find we don't record every
program we do, but we record many. Um,
you can find many of them on our
Washington D.C. History and Culture is
our flagship um, YouTube channel. You
can check that out. Um, as far as
programs we have coming up, we're going
to continue on with our series of the
Old Masters. We're going to be talking
about Vermeer and the Woman with the
Pearl Earring Saturday, March 14th.
Um, Saturday, March 21st we're doing the
Smithsonian Black and African-American
Art. Apologies, we had to reschedule
that program because of work
commitments.
Um, and then in April we're going back
to the Art Institute of Chicago. And
then in mid-April, one of my favorite
artist, Caravaggio. And we're talking
about the Italian Baroque period. Uh, be
on the lookout for that. But before we
do that,
um, Patty, Brad, Joanne, any final
thoughts on Georgia O'Keeffe
before we call it a night?
I I agree with To me, and again, as I
opened up, I mean, they they every
period of her life is great art. Every
period that she
painted in.
Um, but there's something in this one
that seems to like fit her soul in this
period. Mhm.
It's like her soul is present in there.
As well as the flower. The flowers too
seem to do that, but there's something
about the nature landscapes that
uh, yeah, expand across time.
Oh, yeah, I can really feel the
connection that she had
to that place. Not at all. Maybe I'm
reading too much into it maybe because
I've been to New Mexico many times and I
really like it there myself, but
What about you, um, Joanne and Brad? Any
final thoughts on Georgia O'Keeffe in
New Mexico before we call it a night?
Well, I appreciate the comments people
gave and they I think they
uh, they
I've always I've always admired
but I appreciate even more because of
all the insights
people have shown to
you know, this
>> Oh, yeah, people make such fascinating
comments um, chiming in thing I mean,
I've been looking at Georgia O'Keeffe's
artwork for years cuz I was an art
history major. I visit a lot of museum,
but I mean, people bring up bring up
things like that everyone thought of
like, "Oh, I've looked at this painting
one times." And someone will like Patty
or you or Brad bring up something or one
of our audience bring up something never
thought or noticed or whatever. So,
that's really cool.
What about you, Mr. Brad? Any final
thoughts on Georgia O'Keeffe before we
call it a night? I think that this
clearly was her heart place once she
lost her husband and moved out there
permanently.
That was a beautiful place to live. I've
only been to New Mexico once driving
through
in 1967 when I was looking for colleges.
And
I thought you were going to say looking
for LSD.
>> [laughter]
>> I was I was
What were you doing What were you doing
out there, Brad? You were looking for
colleges? Yeah, we we we went out west
to go look at colleges and visit my
grandmother and and
>> Oh, I see. Oh, that's neat.
And Uh, we drove through New Mexico and
it was
a lot of red rock and and a lot of
Indian pueblos, and then uh
we did spend a couple of days in Santa
Fe, which were really fascinating.
See,
that's a great
>> have got my wife on because her my wife
Michelle, part of her family is from
Gallup, New Mexico. Oh, yeah.
There you have it. I like that word you
used though, Brad, that her heart place.
I love that. Yes.
The I remember reading when she first
went there um when she was so
devastated, I I again because of her the
image I have of her, sh- the way she
described how she arrived the first time
in in New Mexico, she was devastated.
She was like trash the way her own
description of it is like she could
barely move, and yet here she finds like
this grounding that that is so different
from any other paintings of her life.
Yes, I agree.
Well, thinking that time a lot of uh
a lot of well-off
uh Easterners and Midwesterners moved
over to New Mexico, and yeah, a lot of
them had artistic
aspirations, and
I've been in New Mexico several times,
and yeah, there was something about
going through uh
the mountains that yeah, it makes you
think of um eternal
of just, you know, getting all the junk
out of your life, all the clutter.
That's a good way to put it.
Um
Any more thoughts on Georgia O'Keeffe,
anybody?
Are there Do you know if there are any
good really good biographies that you
would recommend?
Oh, um yeah, there's one I read in uh
college, but I don't remember the title
of it. I'd have to go look that up.
That's a good question.
There's that movie. I was going to
stream it again someday.
Um
It's like a biopic. It's It's okay. It's
not the greatest movie, but um I was
going to stream that again someday.
Yeah, I vaguely remember we watched that
one night, didn't we?
Mhm.
You're right though, it didn't leave a
huge impression.
Uh like some of the other ones we've
seen.
Yeah, yeah.
1929 and the population was 420,000.
It might have been a small
>> size of a like a
city.
Exactly.
>> And not even a very big city, and that's
spread out across the whole state. The
population are about a quarter of the
borough of Brooklyn.
>> [laughter]
>> All right. Well, let's go ahead and
wrap things up. Thanks everyone for
joining. If you're interested, I'll play
a preview
of a future program we'll be doing about
the American collection at the Art
Institute of Chicago. It'll be a encore
from one we did a few weeks ago.
Uh let me queue that up, and
The strength of her profile though is
just extraordinary. She was such a
striking-looking woman.
Oh, yeah, very distinctive. So, all
right, everyone, well, have a great
evening. Thanks so much for joining us.
Stay safe, and we'll see you next time.
Here's a preview of our upcoming program
on the American collection at the
Institute of Chicago, which ironically
enough has some Georgia O'Keeffe
paintings in it.
Oh,
I think I forgot to do something.
>> [music]
[music]
>> I think it was one of those
>> [music]
[music]